The Life of Muhammadﷺ, The Madinan Period, Volume 1
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
السلام عليكم ورحمة اللهِ و بركاته
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ ۝ بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْراَ
One thing that I forgot to mention
when I was talking about the story of the capture of Ummayyah Bin Khalaf(اُمَيَّة بن خَلَف)
by Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف),
When he was held captive by Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف)
and they were walking through the site of the Battle of Badr(بدر).
Ummayyah(أمَيَّة) asked Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن), he said;
who was that man, who had an ostrich feather across his chest?
So, Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) said, that is Hamza Bin Abdul Muttalib رضي الله عنه,
Ummayyah Bin Khalaf(اُمَيَّة بن خَلَف) said;
هَذَالَّذِيْ فَعَلَ بنا الْأفَاعيْلْ
This is the man who ruined us.
So, Hamza Bin Abdul Muttalib(حمزه بن عبدالمطلب) was truly the lion of Allah,
اَسَدْ الله ورسوله
The lion of Allah and His messenger,
that's something that I just forgot to mention, when I was talking about Ummayyah(أمَيَّه).
We're gonna carry on, with the prisoners of war, we're still talking about that.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in a Hadith(حديث) narrated by Abu Dawood(ابوداؤد),
لَوْ كَانَ المُطْعَمْ بِنْ عُدَيْ حَيًّا ثُمَّ كَلَّمَنِيَّ فِيْ هَؤُلَآءِ النَّتَنْى لَتَرَكْتُهُمْ لًهْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says if Mut'am Ibn Udaye(مطعم إبن عدي) was still alive,
and he talked to me about these prisoners of war,
actually Rasool Allah ﷺ used the word Natan(نتن).
Natan(نتن) means something that has a foul smell.
That is the name that he used to refer to these prisoners of war.
Now probably doesn't literally mean that they were foul smelling,
but what is meant by it is that disbelief is foul smelling, figuratively speaking,
because Allah has called it Rijs(رجس), impurity
so disbelief is an impure thing.
Anyway, Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying the meaning of the Hadith(حديث).
If Mut'am Ibn Udaye(مطعم إبن عدي), If he was alive, and he interceded for these prisoners of war,
I would have released them, for him.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling us that he was grateful to Al-Mut'am Ibn Udaye(المطعم إبن عدي).
Who was a disbeliever
because of his honesty and his good stand towards the Muslims,
even though he was a Mushrik(مشرك) a disbelievers.
And this shows that Rasool Allah ﷺ would act appropriately,
according to the deeds of a person.
So, he would deal with good people Kindly
and he would deal with evil people accordingly.
Now, we don't want to go into either extreme
of being incapable of showing nothing but brutality towards the Kuffar(كفار)
or on the other hand to act in a way that only shows that we are interested in appeasing the Kuffar(كفار).
A Muslim should act in each situation and make a judgment in that situation
according to what is the most wise method of action.
And one should overcome emotions
and one should overcome doing something because of, I'm worried what other people will say,
I'm worried, how our perception will be seen.
I'm worried that I will be giving Islam, a bad picture,
I'm worried about this, I'm worried about that.
We should forget about all of these considerations and do what is right
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying here
if this man was alive, I would have released these prisoners of war for him.
On the other hand,
Rasool Allah ﷺ, specifically chose Uqba Bin Abi Moait(عقبة بن أبي معيط) and An-Nadhar Bin Haris(نضر بن حارث) to be executed
from among all of the other prisoners of war, which totaled 70.
The number of prisoners of war was 70.
Rasool Allah ﷺ calls Uqba Bin Abi Moait(عقبة بن أبي معيط),
and Uqba Bin Abi Moait(عقبة بن أبي معيط) said;
How come, O Messenger of Allah you are choosing me out of everyone else to be killed.
O messenger of Allah, if you're gonna kill the rest of the prisoners of war then kill me with them,
if you're gonna ransom them, than ransom me with them.
How come you are picking me out of everyone else to be executed?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
لِعَدَوَتِكَ لِلهِ وَرَسُوْلِه
Because of your animosity towards Allah and His messenger.
So, Uqba(عُقْبَة) said;
فَمَنْ لِّسِّبِيَّهْ
Who will take care of my children.?
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him, the fire.
قَدِّمْه’ يَا عَاصِمْ اَضْرِبْ عُنُقَهْ
O Asim(عاصم) Pull him forward and behead him.
And he was promptly beheaded by Asim Bin Thabit رضي الله عنه.
While An-Nadhar Bin Haris(النضر بن حارث) also,
Rasool Allah ﷺ, told Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) to execute him.
These two men were specifically handpicked, out of everyone else
because of their evil and Ibn Kathir رضي الله عنه said;
I would comment that these two men were among the most evil of Allah's servants,
the most stubborn, wicked, envious and disbelieving of men
and they had been very active in satirizing Islam and its supporters,
Allah damn them, and he did, indeed.
Uqba Bin Abi Moait(عقبة بن أبي معيط) was the one
who saw Rasool Allah ﷺ in Sujood(سجود) next to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
when Rasool Allah ﷺ was still in Makkah
and he stepped over his neck with his foot.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said, I felt that my eyes were going to pop out
I was gonna die.
And this is also the man who saw me in Rukkoo(ركوع)
and came in threw the intestines of a camel, he threw them over my back
and then Fatimah رضي الله عنها came and remove them.
So, Uqba Bin Abi Moait(عقبة بن أبي معيط) was one of the worst devils of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
And that is why he deserved this severe punishment.
While An-Nadhar Bin Haris(النضر بن حارث) was the one who went to Persia,
to learn the stories of Asfandyaar(أسفند يار) and Rustum(رستم),
and he would come back to Makkah, and tell the people to gather around him and he would say,
come and listen to my stories, they're better than Muhammad(محمد)'s stories.
what makes him more befitting to being a prophet compared to me?
He said, I can tell stories just like he could.
So, what makes him entitled to becoming a prophet, and doesn't give me that right.?
So, he used to sway the people away from the Majlis(مجلس) circle of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, these two men were executed.
So you can contrast this to what Rasool Allah ﷺ said about Al-Mutam Ibn Udae(ألمطعم إبن عدي)
and see how Rasool Allah ﷺ would deal differently with different people.
Now, with these two men, they were executed.
However, with the rest, Rasool Allah ﷺ specifically gave the instructions to the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم and said;
اِسْتَوْصُوْا اَسَرَى خَيْرًا
Treat the prisoners of war kindly,
treat them kindly.
So, Abu Aziz(ابو عزيز), the brother of Mus'ab Bin Umair(مصعب إبن عمير) he said;
كُنْتُ فِيْ الْأَسَارَى يَوْمَ بَدْرٍ، فَقَالَ رَسُول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم اِسْتَوْصُوْ بِلْاَسَرَى خَيْرًا
وَكُنْتُ فِيْ نَفَرٍ مِنَّ الْأَنْصَارِ فَكَانُوْا إِذَا قَدّمُوْا عَشَاءَهُمْ
اَوْغَدَاءَهُمْ أَكَّلُوْا التَّمْرَ وَاَطْعَمُوْنِيْ الْبُرَّة (خَصّونِي بالخبز) ؛ لِوَصِيَّةِ رَسول الله
He said, I was with a group of Ansaar(اَنْصَار), bringing me from Badr(بدر),
when they had their lunch and dinner,
they would give me the bread and ate the dates themselves,
in accordance with instruction given them by Rasool Allah ﷺ regarding us,
every piece of bread that came into their hands, they passed on to me,
I was embarrassed and would return the bread, but they would pass it back untouched.
Bread was the better food compared to dates,
so they would eat the dates and they would give him the bread.
And they would just survive on eating dates.
So, they would give him actually they would give him a better treatment, than they would give themselves.
Ibn Hishaam(إبن هشام), he comments on this. He said;
This Abu Aziz(ابوعزيز) was the standard bearer of the Mushrikeen(مشركين) at Badr(بدر), following An-Nadhar Bin Haris(النضر بن حارث).
So, Abu Aziz(ابوعزيز) wasn't just a foot soldier
Abu Aziz(ابو عزيز) was the standard bearer on the Battle of Badr(بدر)
and still Rasool Allah ﷺ has told to treat such men, well.
Abul Aas Bin Ar-Rabiy(ابوالعاص بن الربيع), he said;
كُنْتُ فِيْ رَاهط مِّنَّ الْاَنْصَارِ جَزَآءَهُمُ اللهُ خَيْرًا
كُنَّا اِذَ تَعَشَّيْنَا اَوْ تَغَدَّيْنَا آثرُوْنِيْ بِالخُبْزْ
Pretty much the same thing.
Al-Waleed Bin Waleed Bin Mugheera(ألوليد بن وليد بن مغيرة), he would say;
وَكَانُوْ يَحْمِلُوْنَنَا وَيَمْشُوْنْ
They would walk while we would ride.
So, the prisoners of war are riding,
while the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم are walking.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله),
see this good treatment is what caused many of these prisoners of war to become Muslim.
Throughout the battles of Rasool Allah ﷺ, we would hear about people who were arrested or captured
and then they would become Muslim and stayed behind.
And some of them to show and prove that they're not becoming Muslim for fear of the sword.
After they are released, they would go back to their people
and then they would come back to Rasool Allah ﷺ and become Muslim.
To prove that we have became Muslim of our own initiative,
not because any pressure, we weren't pressured into it.
For example, Abu Aziz(ابو عزيز), he ended up becoming Muslim.
The brother of Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير), when he saw, how the Muslims were treating him.
They would treat him better than their own selves
So, Akhlaaq(أخلاق) are important even with your enemy,
even with the enemy, the Muslim should deal with him, in a good way with dignity.
I mean, a Muslim is not cruel, a Muslim is not wicked, a Muslim is not deceptive,
a Muslim is not a liar,
a Muslim deals with everyone with honesty, dignity, straightforwardness
and kindness towards all of the creation of Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
except those who deserve to be dealt cruelly like Uqba Bin Abi Moait(عقبة بن أبي معيط), and An-Nadhar Bin Haris(النضر بن حارث)
because these are people who are so evil you can't afford, treating them kindly,
treating them kindly is actually being fooled by them,
because these are people who are going to turn around and harm the Muslims.
Al-Abbas Ibn Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب), the uncle of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه said;
Ransom yourself, pay your ransom.
Al-Abbas(العباس) said, O Messenger of Allah, I'm a Muslim.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
اَمَّا ظَاهِرُكَ فَكَانَ عَلَيْنَا
What was evident was that you were against us.
Allah knows best about your accepting Islam.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is here setting for us, a rule,
We go by what we see.
We do not and cannot know what is in the hearts.
Only Allahعَزّوجَلّ is, the One, Who can see the hearts,
we go by what we see. R
asool Allah ﷺ is telling Al-Abbas(العباس),
Allah is the one who knows whether you're Muslim or not,
what we can see is that you were against us,
you were fighting us, you were in the army of the enemy.
So, we're going to go by that
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he said, when he was Khalifah(خليفه),
In the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Revelation would come down and tell us, what is in the hearts of men.
But now we're going to go by what we see.
We're going to make our judgments based on what appears from you.
If what appears from you is Islam, we will accept that,
and if what appears from you is disbelief,
we will assume that you are disbeliever,
even if you claim that you are otherwise.
If your actions are those of a disbeliever
it doesn't benefit you to say that you are a Muslim,
We will go by your actions.
So, the action of Al-Abbas(العباس) here was, that he was with the enemy
You can claim that you are a Muslim, you can state;
لا اله الا الله
But why were you on the enemies side.?
And this is a very important rule,
we should not judge people, according to what is in their hearts, we judge them by their action.
In the same time, we don't allow people to fool us by stating,
that they are this and that when their actions prove otherwise.
we go by the actions of people that is how we judge people.
So, somebody who's acting as a disbeliever in and out,
cannot come on fool us and trick us and say; I'm a Muslim
Al-Abbas(العباس) said; I don't have any money.
Rasool Allahﷺ told him; What about the money that you buried in the ground,
and you told your wife, Ummal-Fadhal(أم الفضل), if I am killed, then make use of this money.
Al-Abbas(العباس) said: I testify and bear witness that you are a messenger of Allah,
no one knew of that treasure of mine, except me and my wife.
So, he did pay for his ransom.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed the Ayah(آية);
يَا أَيُّهَا النَّبِيُّ قُلْ لِمَنْ فِي أَيْدِيكُمْ مِنَ الْأَسْرَىٰ
إِنْ يَعْلَمِ اللَّهُ فِي قُلُوبِكُمْ خَيْرًا يُؤْتِكُمْ خَيْرًا مِمَّا أُخِذَ مِنْكُمْ وَيَغْفِرْ لَكُمْ ۗ
وَاللَّهُ غَفُورٌ رَحِيمٌ ّ۝
وَإِنْ يُرِيدُوا خِيَانَتَكَ فَقَدْ خَانُوا اللَّهَ مِنْ قَبْلُ فَأَمْكَنَ مِنْهُمْ ۗ وَاللَّهُ عَلِيمٌ حَكِيمٌ۝
O Prophet, say to whoever is in your hands of the captives.
If Allah knows any good in your hearts,
He will give you better than what was taken from you,
and He will forgive you and Allah's Forgiving and Merciful.
But if they intend to betray you,
Then they have already betrayed Allah before
and he empowered you over them and Allah is Knowing and Wise.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ is telling these, men who claim that they were Muslim
and they had to pay for the ransom.
If you are Muslim,
Allahعَزّوجَلّ will replace that money that was taken from you, Don't worry.!
Al-Abbas(العباس) said that I paid 20 Uoqia(أوقيه) of gold.
This is a certain weight of gold, I paid that for my ransom.
And then Allahعَزّوجَلّ has given me much more than that.
Meaning Allahعَزّوجَلّ has replaced that money that he paid for ransom
and Allahعَزّوجَلّ has multiplied it for Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib رضي الله عنه.
Abul Aas(ابو العاص) was the husband of Zainab(زينب) Bint(بنت) Rasool Allah ﷺ.
He was a Mushrik(مشرك),
so the daughter of Rasool Allah ﷺ up until that point was married to a disbelievers.
This was before the ruling came down preventing Muslim women from remaining with their disbelieving husbands,
this was before that ruling.
And she was in Makkah,
so she wants to free her husband,
Zainab(زينب) Bint Rasool Allah ﷺ, she wants to free her husband Al-Aas(ألعاص).
So, let me read to you what Ibn Is'haaq(ابن اسحاق) said about this situation.
Actually, I will read you the story of her coming back.
But before that let's just talk about the ransoming.
So, Zainabرضي الله عنها , she sends an amount of money sufficient to release her husband from captivity.
She also sends along with that money a necklace.
This necklace was given to her as a gift by her mother Khadijah(خديجه),
when she got married.
This was her wedding gift, from her mother.
So, the necklace belonged to Khadijah(خديجه)
and then Khadijah(خديجه) gave it as a gift to her daughter when she got married.
So, Zainab(زينب) sends this necklace.
When the necklace falls in the hands of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
it brought back memories of his wife Khadijah رحمة الله عليها,
and we know that Rasool Allah ﷺ was very soft hearted, kind, compassionate and this touched him.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told the Ansaar(أنصار) who were holding her husband.
He said: If you should think fit to deliver her prisoner to her,
and to return to her, what is hers then do so.
And they immediately released him
and they released them without ransom.
And they sent back also the necklace.
Now Rasool Allah ﷺ, placed a condition on the release of Abul Aas(ابوالعاص).
And that condition was you never assist an enemy against us,
and you send to me, Zainab(زينب).
So, Abul Aas(ابوالعاص) was a man of his word.
When he went back to Makkah
He allowed Zainab(زينب) to leave Makkah and go to her father.
Ibn Is'haaq says; so she continued making plans.
When she was ready, her husband's brother, Kinanah Ibn Rabiyah(كنانة إبن ربيعه) brought a camel which she mounted.
And he taking his bow and quiver, led her away.
She riding in a Haudaj(هودج), and it being daytime.
Some of the Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) men discussed this and followed after her
catching up with her Dhu Tuwaa(ذو طوى),
the first to reach her was Habbar Ibn Aswad Ibn Al-Muttalib(هبار إبن أسود إبن المطلب).
He scared her with his spear as she was there in the Haudaj(هودج).
And because as they claimed, she was pregnant at the time, she suffered a miscarriage.
Her brother in law then knelt down and took the arrows from his quiver, saying,
By Allah, if any man comes near me, I'll put an arrow into him,
the man drew away from him.
Then Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) arrived with some other Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) leaders and said,
Put down your arrows, so we can talk with you.
He did so and Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) drew near him and said;
You have not done well.
You came forth with a woman openly going over people's heads,
even though you're aware of the injury and damage done us by Muhammad(محمد).
When you took away his daughter openly, and regardless of anyone else,
that people thought this was due to the humiliation we have undergone,
and that this reflected our weakness and in capacity,
I swear we don't want to keep her from her father
and we're not after revenge.
But you'd better return back then you can secretly take her away to her father.
So it shows you, that these Kuffar(كفار) of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), they respected woman,
unlike some of the enemies of Allahعَزّوجَلّ, today who are willing to violate the rights of Muslim women and Muslim children,
but these Kuffar(كفار) they still had some dignity in their hearts and Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان) said,
as long as you're going to take her away secretly, we don't have a problem with that.
Anyway, and she reached Madina safely.
Abu Izza(أبوعزة) another prisoner of war,
he said, O Messenger of Allah, You know, my state of finances,
I am poor and have a family.
So, be gracious to me.
Abu Izza(أبوعزة) had daughters to take care of, and he was poor.
Rasool Allah ﷺ appreciated, he was consider it of his situation.
So he told him, I'm gonna allow you to be freed.
However my condition is that you do not support anyone else against me.
This time you came out fighting against me in the Battle of Badr(بدر),
next time you refuse to fight against Muhammadﷺ and the Muslims.
Abu Izza(أبوعزة) agreed.
However, in the Battle of Uhud(أحد), the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), were able to seduce him, into joining them.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), again, he fell into the hands of the Muslims.
This time he tried to use the same excuse again,
and said; O Messenger of Allah, I have daughters, I'm poor, let me go.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him, I will not let you stroke your beard and say,
that you have deceived Muhammad(محمد) twice.
So, Muhammadﷺ wasn't sentimental, and he wasn't a leader that could be tricked or deceived.
He was kind, he was compassionate, he was tolerant,
but in the same time, he would not allow people to take advantage of these good qualities and harm the Muslims.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told him, I already allowed you once I'm not gonna allow you again.
And he ordered his execution, at the spot.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ said: A believer will not be bitten twice from the same layer.
A believer will not be tricked twice,
a believer should not allow himself to be bitten twice from the same source.
So, this is an important lesson for the Muslims.
We shouldn't be gullible and fall prey to deceptive words,
muslims should be alert and should know what and who are their benifit islam and muslims
and who are up to no good.
Suhail Ibn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو), one of the nobility,
one of the leaders of the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
He was taken as a POW.
He used to speak against Islam.
He was a fluent and good eloquent speaker.
So, Umar Bin Khattabرضي الله عنه said;
O Rasool Ullah; "Let me extract, the two front teeth of Suhail Ibn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو),
so his tongue will protrude and he will never speak ill of you again.
Umar Bin Khattab(عمر بن خطاب) wanted to mutilate his mouth pull out his teeth,
so that he won't be able to speak properly again.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; I will not mutilate him,
because Allah could mutilate me,
meaning this is not the Islamic way, treating enemies even if they are enemies
and Rasool Allah ﷺ then said;
"Maybe he will take a stand for which you will not criticize him."
Maybe one day, this tongue of his, which was used for evil,
will be an instrument of good.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) that did happen as Rasool Allah ﷺ stated,
when Rasool Allah ﷺ died and all of the Arabs apostated.
Suhail Ibn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو), was the reason, for the steadfastness of the people of Makkah.
He stood up and said;
يَا مَعْشَرَقُرَيْشْ لَا تَكُوْنُوْا آخِرَ النَّاسِ اِسْلَامًا وَاَوَّلَّهُمْ رِدَّةْ مَنْ رَابَنَا ضَرَبْنَا عُنُقَا
O people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), Don't be the last people to enter Islam and the first people to leave it.
Whoever we are suspicious of, we will behead him.
And these words kept the people of Makkah firm on Islam,
even though they were new Muslims and their Islam could have been weak,
because it didn't take deep roots in their hearts yet,
but because of these words of Suhail Ibn Amr(سهيل إبن عمرو), they remained Muslims.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told the prisoners of war,
who could teach reading and writing, the ones who were illiterate.
He said, If you teach 10 children to read and write, that will be your ransom, you will be freed.
And this shows you the importance that was placed on literacy and on education,
اِقْرَأْ بِاسْمِ رَبِّكَ الَّذِي خَلَقَ
were the first Ayaat(آيات) revealed to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Finally, the ruling of POW's, the Islamic ruling on POW's.
It is up to the leader, it is up to the Muslim Imam(امام) to determine the fate of POW's.
He has the choice of executing them,
example is Uqba Bin Abi Moait(عقبة بن أبي معيط) and An-Nadhar Bin Hariss(ألنضر بن حارث),
who were executed by Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Number two,
He can free them without ransom as he did with Abu Izza(ابوعزة) and Abul Aas(ابوالعاص),
he can free them with ransom, like he did with the rest of the POW's.
And he has the option of enslaving the POW's
such as the ruling of Saad Bin Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) on Bannu Quraidha(بنو قريظة),
as we'll talk about later on.
So these are the rulings of POW's in Islam.
We have our own Geneva Convention, we don't have to abide by anyone's Geneva Convention.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ has already taught us, what is right and what is wrong.
So Muslims have their own rules which are part of the Sharia(شريعة) of Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
and it has the Hidaya(هداية) that Muslims would need,
فِيْهِ اَلْهُدَى
Usaid Bin Khuzair رضي الله عنه, he came to Rasool Allah ﷺ, after the Battle of Badr(بدر) and he said;
O Messenger of Allah, We didn't know that any fighting would have occurred otherwise we would have followed you,
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him, You are speaking the truth.
So, some of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار), who stayed behind.
They stayed behind, not because they didn't want to fight
but because they didn't think that fighting would happen.
Because we said that the original intent of the army, was to raid the caravan and not to meet an army.
What is the status of the people of Badr(بدر)?
Well the people of Badr(بدر) carry a special status.
Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and asked him,
مَا تَعُدُّوْنَ اَهْلَ بَدْرٍ فِيْكُمْ
What do you consider the people of Badr(بدر) among you to be.?
What is the status of the people of Badr(بدر) among you?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; They are among the best of the Muslims.
Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) said; the same is the case with the angels, who attended Badr(بدر).
So, Badr(بدر) wasn't a special event for the Muslims, who attended it,
but it was also a special event for the angels who attended it.
The Muslims who attended Badr(بدر) are the best of Muslims
and the angels who attended Badr(بدر) are the best of angels.
And that's why, in our books the people of Badr(بدر) are considered to be a special class,
you know Tabaqat-Al-Badriyeen(طبقة البدرين),
the class of the people of Badr(بدر), they are special class.
When Hatib Ibn Abi Baltaa(حاطب بن أبي بلتعة) committed an act of treason,
against Allah and His Messenger,
by informing the people of Makkah of the plans of Rasool Allah ﷺ to attack them.
Umar Bin Khattab(عمر بن خطاب) came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
O Messenger of Allah, Let me execute him.
He is a Munafiq(منافق).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: O Umar(عُمَر), Probably Allah has looked down at the people of Badr(بدر) and said;
Do whatever you want because I have forgiven you
Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying that the people of Badr(بدر), because of attending Badr(بدر),
Allah looked at them and said, You can now, do whatever you want,
because I have forgiven you.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ said that, the eyes of Umar(عُمَر) swelled with tears.
Hatib Bin Abi Baltaa(حاطب بن أبي بلتعة), was one of the Muslims, who attended Badr(بدر).
And because of that, Allahعَزّوجَلّ has granted them forgiveness.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in another Hadith(حديث),
No one who attended Badr(بدر) or Hudaybiyah(حديبية) will enter into Hell fire.
So, the people of Badr(بدر) are special.
Some of the consequences of the Battle of Badr(بدر).
Number one, hypocrisy.
There were many people in Madina, who were not happy to see the Muslims victorious.
But they're not strong enough to publicly declare that.
So, they went underground.
They publicly professed Islam.
Outwardly you can't tell the difference between them and the Muslims.
They pray like Muslims, they fast like Muslims, they pay Zakah(زكواة) like Muslims.
They attend the gatherings of Muslims, they attend the lessons of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
But deep in their hearts, they despised Islam.
They hate the Muslims, and they wish that Islam would vanish from the face of the earth.
They wish that Islam did not come to Madina.
And these were Al-Munafiqoon(ألمنافقون),
But because Islam was now victorious, and the Muslims were strong,
and the power of Rasool Allah ﷺ in Madina was increasing,
they dared not speak their minds.
So, they were jumping the bandwagon.
And they were plotting underground against the Muslims.
And the hypocrites were an extremely dangerous enemy,
we could probably say that they're the most dangerous enemy of all,
because they were living with the Muslims, and they knew the secrets of the Muslims.
And they were passing on these secrets to the outside enemies of Islam.
So they were a fifth column.
These were the ones, who're delivering the news to Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
these were the ones, who were assisting the enemies of Allah, in their planning against the messenger of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
So, it was a very dangerous situation,
and it's a very difficult enemy to deal with.
Because they don't go public with their disbelief,
and they are blending perfectly among the Muslim community.
Rasool Allah ﷺ himself didn't know about many of these hypocrites.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says; You don't know them, we know them.
So, even Rasool Allah ﷺ did not know the names of some of these Munafiqeen(منافقين),
until later on, when they were revealed to him by Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Allahسبحانه تعالى says about them;
وَإِذَا لَقُوا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا قَالُوا آمَنَّا
وَإِذَا خَلَوْا إِلَىٰ شَيَاطِينِهِمْ قَالُوا إِنَّا مَعَكُمْ إِنَّمَا نَحْنُ مُسْتَهْزِئُونَ۝
When they meet those who believe they say we believe,
but when they are alone with their evil ones,
they say indeed we are with you, we were only mockers.
So, when they're with the Muslims, they say we are like you, we are Muslim.
So, this was a consequence of the Battle of Badr(بدر)
that now you have this new category of people Al-Munafiqoon(ألمنافقون),
before you had kuffar(كفار) and Muslims,
now you have Kuffar(كفار) Munafiqoon(منافقون) and Muslims,
now Munafiqoon(منافقون) are part of Kuffar(كفار), but the difference is that they claim to be Muslim.
Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب) was one of the devil's of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
He was sitting with Safwaan Ibn Ummayyah(صفوان إبن اُمَيَّة) next to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
And he said, If it wasn't for the fact that I'm in debt, and I have children to care for
I would go and assassinate Muhammad(محمد) myself.
So, Safwaan(صفوان) took advantage of that and he said,
I will pay your debt and I'll take care of your children, if anything happens to you.
So, Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب) agreed with Safwaan(صفوان), that he will travel to Madina,
with the intent of assassinating Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So he dips his sword and poison, until it absorbs, the poison
and then he rushes towards Madina.
He enters Madina and he passes next to a gathering that included Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was talking to some men, about the Battle of Badr(بدر).
He was talking to people who didn't attend it.
You know Badr(بدر) was all, what they were talking about.
A great victory, everyone is happy.
They are narrating all of the stories of what went on.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) spots Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب) and he said,
this enemy of Allah, This dog, Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب) is not here for any good.
And he stands up and he grabs Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب)
and he wraps the sheath of his sword around his neck.
And then he takes him to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he says, O Messenger of Allah, this enemy of Allah did not come for any good.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said, Let him go Umar(عُمَر), release him.
So, he was released by Umar(عُمَر).
But then Umar(عُمَر) told some of the Sahabah outside, Be careful, and guard Rasool Allah ﷺ,
so Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب) comes in and he said;
عمت صباحا
Good Morning
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Allah has replaced us with a better greeting than that
اَلسلام عليكم ورحمة الله
Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب) said, you haven't been using that for long,
meaning that, you just changed your tradition and your customs.
Otherwise before, you used to say good morning just like us.
Anyway, Rasool Allah ﷺ told him: Why did you come?
He said: I came to ask for the release of my son.
His son Wahb(وهب) was a POW, that was his cover story.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him, Tell me the truth. Why did you come?
He said; that's why, I came, I came to ask for the release of my son.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him; So why are you carrying a sword?
He said;
تَبَّتْ الَّهَا مِنْ سُيُوْفُهَا الْاَغْنَتْ عَنَّا شَيْاً
Woe to these swords, they haven't done us any good.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him; You are lying.
The reason, why you came is because you met with Safwaan(صفوان) next to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
And you told him
that if it wasn't for the fact that you are in debt, and you have children to take care of,
you would come and assassinate me.
And then Safwaan(صفوان) told you,
I will take care of your debt and your children, If anything happens to you.
And then you agreed with Safwaan(صفوان) that you will keep, this issue secret and you'll tell nobody about it.
Umair(عمير) said:
اَشْهَدُ اَنَّكَ رَسُوْلُ الله
I testify that you are the messenger of Allah
because no one overheard that conversation between me and Safwaan(صفوان).
So only Allahعَزّوجَلّ could tell you about that conversation
and he became Muslim.
And he goes back to Makkah, and on his way back, Safwaan(صفوان) was telling the people of Makkah,
soon you will hear news that will make you forget what happened in Badr(بدر).
He would go around telling them, soon the good news will come.
You're going to hear some good news, it's on its way.
But then Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب) comes back declaring Islam.
Safwaan(صفوان) said: I'm never going to speak to him again.
Now, Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب), who was a devil of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) now becomes a Daiyah(داعيه),
and instead of persecuting Muslims as he used to do,
he would persecute the people, who would persecute Muslims.
And many people became Muslim through the Da'wah(دعوة) of Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب), Allah Ho Akbar(الله اكبر).
Some lessons from the Battle of Badr(بدر).
Number one, victory is from Allah,
after victory, normally, soldiers will be very proud of their training, their skill, their bravery.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ never ever praised the Muslims for their victory, never.
Look at the Ayaat(آيات) that commented on the victory of Muslims.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَمَا جَعَلَهُ اللَّهُ إِلَّا بُشْرَىٰ لَكُمْ وَلِتَطْمَئِنَّ قُلُوبُكُمْ بِهِ ۗ
وَمَا النَّصْرُ إِلَّا مِنْ عِنْدِ اللَّهِ الْعَزِيزِ الْحَكِيمِ۝
And victory is not except from Allah, the Exalted in Might and Wise.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
فَلَمْ تَقْتُلُوهُمْ وَلَٰكِنَّ اللَّهَ قَتَلَهُمْ ۚ
وَمَا رَمَيْتَ إِذْ رَمَيْتَ وَلَٰكِنَّ اللَّهَ رَمَىٰ ۚ
And you did not kill them, but it was Allah, who kill them
And You threw not, O Muhammad(محمد) when you threw, but it was Allah, who threw,
that He might test the believers with a good test.
So, who does the credit go to.? Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ is dealing with the aftermath of victory,
He is dealing with the potential of or the probability of Muslims feeling pride
and having confidence in their abilities or attributing the victory to their abilities.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ is telling them, the victory was a blessing from Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
It came from Allahعَزّوجَلّ, it was Allahعَزّوجَلّ, Who gave you that victory?
And for example, when the Muslims came to congratulate Rasool Allah ﷺ,
so one of those Sahabah responded back by saying,
Why are you congratulating us? What are you congratulating us for?
إن لَقينا إلا عجائزَ صُلعًا
We have only met old bald men, like camels waiting for slaughter and we slaughtered them.
So, he's like saying, it was so easy,
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him; Don't say that, O, cousin, Those were the leaders.
It was Allah, Who made it easy.
This was a formidable foe, it was a strong foe,
don't belittle their ability and strength.
But the victory that you achieved was because Allahعَزّوجَلّ made it easy for you.
So, this is very important,
that whatever victory we achieve in any avenue of life,
we attribute it to the one, it belongs to, and that is Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
whether you are successful in your business,
whether you are successful in your education,
whether you are successful with your family,
whether you are successful as a Daiyah(داعيه),
whether you are successful as an Imam(امام), or scholar,
attribute it, to the one it belongs to and that is Allah.
Don't be like Qaroon(قارون), who said;
إِنَّمَا أُوتِيتُهُ عَلَىٰ عِلْمٍ عِنْدِي ۚ
I have this wealth because of my skill, because of my knowledge.
That's the first lesson.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says, in another Ayah(آية) that I forgot to mention,
وَاذْكُرُوا إِذْ أَنْتُمْ قَلِيلٌ مُسْتَضْعَفُونَ فِي الْأَرْضِ تَخَافُونَ أَنْ يَتَخَطَّفَكُمُ النَّاسُ
فَآوَاكُمْ وَأَيَّدَكُمْ بِنَصْرِهِ وَرَزَقَكُمْ مِنَ الطَّيِّبَاتِ لَعَلَّكُمْ تَشْكُرُونَ۝
And remember when you were few and oppressed in the land fearing that people might abduct you.
That is who, you were, you were few, you were oppressed
and you used to fear that people might abduct you, but He sheltered you
supported you with His victory, and provided you with good things that you might be grateful.
Some of the miracles, that occurred in Badr(بدر).
The reducing of numbers insight, we talked about that.
The rain, the sleep,
they slept very well, the night before the battle.
The angels coming down.
Ummayyah Bin Khalaf(اُمَيَّة بن خلف)
because Rasool Allah ﷺ said that he will be killed and his prophecy was fulfilled.
The Sword of Ukasha(عكاشه),
he had the wooden sword and Rasool Allah ﷺ held it and it turns into a real sword, that's another miracle.
The killing of the Imams(اِمَام) of Kuffr(كفر), that's a miracle because before the Battle, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
this is where so and so will be killed, this is where so and so will be killed,
this is where so and so will be killed,
and they were killed exactly in the spots that were pointed by Rasool Allah ﷺ.
The Eye of Qatadah(قتاده).
Qatada(قتاده), had one of his eyes fall out of its socket and it was only hanging by the nerve.
And they were about to cut it.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ told them not to do so.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ held the eye, placed it back in its socket, and then wiped it.
Qatada(قتاده), would say that that eye became stronger than my other eye.
That's a miracle of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Knowing the whereabouts of the money of Al-Abbas(العباس).
Revealing the assassination plot that Wahb Ibn Umair(عمير إبن وهب) was planning.
All of these are miracles that happened in Badr(بدر),
so you can see that yes, Qur'an is the greatest miracle of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
but he had so many physical miracles, many more than probably any other Prophet.
A word on the miracles of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and I think I spoke about this, in some of my other talks.
Most of the miracles of Rasool Allah ﷺ occurred in the context of Jihad(جهاد).
And also most of the karmaat(كرامات) of the Auliyaa(أوليآء) of Allahعَزّوجَلّ occur in the context of Jihad(جهاد).
So really, jihad(جهاد) is where the Karamaat(كرامات) happen.
The next lesson Wala'a and Bara'a(ألولآء ولبرآء),
Loyalty to Allah and His Messenger and the believers,
and disassociating oneself from disbelief.
Few examples from Badr(بدر).
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was on the Muslim side and his son was on the side of Al-Kuffar(ألكفار), his son Abdur Rahman(عبدالرحمن).
Abdur Rahman Ibn Abu Bakr(عبدالرحمن ابن ابوبكر) said,
he told his father later on, when he became Muslim, he said;
O, my father, I saw you on the day of Badr(بدر)
but I would avoid you.
Because I didn't want to attack you.
Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) said;
I didn't see you and If I saw you, I would have pursued you and killed you.
So, Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) was willing to fight his own son, for the sake of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
We talked about the story of Abu Hudaifah(ابوحذيفه)
and his father Utba(عتبة), when he saw that his father was buried in Al-Qulaib(ألقليب).
Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب إبن عمير) and his brother Abu Aziz(ابوعزيز), who was a POW
Mus'ab(مصعب) passed by the Ansaar(أنْصَار), who were holding Abu Aziz(ابوعزيز)
and he told them, tie his hands fast, tighten the ropes, on Abu Aziz(ابوعزيز),
because his mother is wealthy, and she'll ransom him for you.
So, Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله),
Is this an advice that Mus'ab(مصعب) should give, to the ones who are holding his brother?
Hold him well tighten the ropes that are tying him because his mother will ransom him.
So, his brother was amazed, his brother said; Brother, Is this how you treat me?
Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب إبن عمير) said, He's more my brother than you are.
He was pointing to the men who are holding him,
he was pointing to the Ansaar(أنْصَار), who are holding him and he said,
these are my real brothers, you are not.
These are my brothers, because of Islam.
And even though you are my blood brother, but your Kuffr(كفر) has separated between us.
Another issue relating to Wala'a and Bara'a(ألولآء ولبرآء).
There were some of the young men of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
who were interested in Islam and actually did become Muslim.
And these were sons of some of the noble families of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم) did they become Muslim, because they sincerely believed in Islam,
or they become Muslim because it was a revolt against the status quo, and they're just interested in it as a fad.
Like we will see among some of the youth of today,
they just want to embrace some things because they're different, I mean, it makes them different.
So these were wealthy young kids in Makkah, and they became Muslim,
such as Ali Bin Ummayyah Bin Khalaf(علي بن أميه بن خلف)
and Abul Qais Bin Al-Waleed Bin Mugheera(ابو القيس بن وليد بن مغيره),
and Abul Qais Bin Fakeh(ابو القيس بن فاكه),
and Al-Haris Bin Zama'a(ألحارث بن زمعة), and Al-Aas Bin Munnabbah(ألعاص بن منبه).
These were all sons of the wealthy men of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
They became Muslim, but they couldn't withstand the demands of Islam,
the sacrifice that the slam asks from you.
So they stayed behind them, they didn't make Hijrah(هجرة), they weren't willing.
These are spoiled kids, they weren't willing to go through the hassle of Hijrah(هجرة) and all of that,
you know will be Muslim if it's convenient, but if it's gonna cost us too much, then forget about it.
So, they stayed behind.
And in fact, they joined with their fathers and their tribe in the Battle of Badr(بدر).
Ibn Hishaam(ابن هشام) says, All of them were killed on the Battle of Badr(بدر).
So, the Muslim said, Well, you know, these were Muslim.
Probably they don't want to go out and fight and they're Muslim.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed. Verse 97. of Surat-Un-Nissa(سورة النساء),
talking about them,
إِنَّ الَّذِينَ تَوَفَّاهُمُ الْمَلَائِكَةُ ظَالِمِي أَنْفُسِهِمْ
قَالُوا فِيمَ كُنْتُمْ ۖ قَالُوا كُنَّا مُسْتَضْعَفِينَ فِي الْأَرْضِ ۚ
قَالُوا أَلَمْ تَكُنْ أَرْضُ اللَّهِ وَاسِعَةً فَتُهَاجِرُوا فِيهَا ۚ
فَأُولَٰئِكَ مَأْوَاهُمْ جَهَنَّمُ ۖ وَسَاءَتْ مَصِيرًا۝
I want you, the listener to think about this.
What do you think their fate is?
They were Muslim,
But they didn't go far enough, in sacrificing for Islam,
they stayed behind and then they ended up being killed in the Battle of Badr(بدر).
Probably they've never shot an arrow
probably they never struck with a sword.
They just went out in the army because they had to,
you know, a soldier is called to duty.
What do you think their fate was?
Allahعَزّوجَلّ said;
Indeed, those whom the angels take in death while wronging themselves,
the angels will say, in what condition were you?
They will say; we were oppressed in the land.
They, the angels will say,
was not the earth of Allah spacious enough for you to immigrate therein.?
For those, their refuge is hell
and evil it is as a destination.
So, don't play around with Islam.
Don't fool around with it.
This is a serious religion.
And you need to be serious.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says in Qur'an,
يَا يَحْيَىٰ خُذِ الْكِتَابَ بِقُوَّةٍ ۖ
O Yahya(يحيى) hold the book with strength, hold it strong.
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ tells Banni Israel(بني إسرائيل),
خُذُوا مَا آتَيْنَاكُم بِقُوَّةٍ
Hold fast, what we have given you.
So, this religion does not accept half hearted effort
and giving it part time, or being a Muslim when it's convenient.
And doing otherwise when it's not.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ has promised you Jannah(جنة) but you have to pay a price.
In the Tafseer(تفسير) of this Ayyah(آية) by Ibn Kathir(إبن كثير).
He mentions a few narrations. One of them is by Bukhari(بخاريْ),
It says that Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) said: that this Ayah(آية) is talking about some Muslims
who were with the disbelievers adding to their numbers,
meaning that they didn't really go out to fight, they just went because they had to.
A soldier responding to the call of duty, they had to go out.
يَاْتِي السَّهَمْ يَرْمِيْ بِهِ فَيُصِيْب اَحَدُهُمْ فَيَقْتُلُ اَوْ يَضْرِبْ عُنُقُهُ فَيُقْتَلْ
And while they're in the army, an arrow would come and kill one of them
and a blow from a sword would kill another
and blow from the spear with kill a third
That's how they died.
And these are the ones whom Allah revealed this Ayah(آية) about.
So, their Islam did not benefit them,
because they didn't make Hijrah(هجرة) and they went out with the army of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
And I think, need to think very deeply about this particular situation because of the implications of it,
the implications of it are very important.
You don't want to die and then have the angels telling you that your reward is hellfire.
We ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to forgive us all, to grant us Jannah(جنة).
And we ask Him to spare us, from the punishment of hellfire.
Another lesson; Istighasah(إستغاثه)
seeking assistance from Allah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, after he prepared the army, and train them
and lined them up
and gave them his instructions and chose the best location.
After all of that, he went aside and he started making Dua(دعا).
And that is the meaning of Tawakkul(توكل).
Tawakkul(توكل) means that you do your best.
You exhaust the worldly means, and then you depend on Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ, he did his best, in terms of everything that he was capable of doing, in this world
in terms of preparing for this battle.
And after that, he started making Dua(دُعَا) to Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
So, don't think that Allah will give you victory.
If you sit at home comfortable on your couch
and just raise your hands and say O Allah, give me victory,
O Allah give them victory, O Allah give the Muslim Ummah(امة) victory.
You have to stand up and do something,
you have to do your best and then you ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to give you, and this applies to everything,
This is the issue of Tawakkul(توكل).
You know, some people have an understanding of Tawakkul(توكل)
that is not really Tawakkul(توكل), this is what is called Tawaakul(تواكل),
like those whom were walking lazily, you know, pretending as if they are Zuhaad(زهاد).
And Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) saw them, he said: Who are these?
They said these are Al-Muttawakkiloon(ألمتوكلون).
These are the ones, who have Tawakkal(توكل) in Allah.
So, he went and beat them with his stick and said;
you know that the sky doesn't rain, gold and silver, you have to go out and work.
So the meaning of Tawakkul(توكل) is
what Rasool Allah ﷺ mentioned in the Hadith(حديث),
he said if you have the right Tawakkul(توكل) on Allah,
Allah will give you, provide for you, like he provides for the birds,
they leave in the morning hungry and they come back at evening full.
So, here the birds didn't stay at home, they went out, worked for the entire day.
And that is the meaning of Tawakkul(توكل).
So, Tawakkul(توكل) is, you do your best but you do not depend on your effort,
you do not depend on your intelligence, you do not dependent on anything in this world.
But you depend on Allah.
So Yes, Rasool Allah ﷺ prepared the army,
Yes, he lined them up,
Yes, he gave them instructions
but he didn't depend on that.
He went aside And he started making Dua(دُعَا) and he was so involved in the Dua(دُعَا)
and the Dua(دُعَا) was so long, Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه felt sorry for him,
and said: O Rasool Allah, that's enough.
Allah will give you, what He promised to you, Allah already promised you.
So, we have to have Istighasah(إستغاثه) on Allahعَزّوجَلّ, depend on Allahعَزّوجَلّ
but you also have to do your best.
So, we don't just do our best and then forget about the Dua(دُعَا).
And we don't just do the Dua(دُعَا) and forget about doing our best,
they both go hand in hand.
This is the end of our commentary on the Battle of Badr(بدر).
In Sha Allah Ta'ala(اِن شاءالله تعالى) in our next session,
we'll talk about events that occurred between Badr(بدر) and Uhud(أحَد).
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلمْ
وَالسلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته